Register of the Ainars Ikstens collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Ainars Ikstens collection
1893-2007
2011C34
Ikstens, Ainars
5 manuscript boxes (2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection is comprised of printed matter relating primarily to the history of Latvia in the 20th century, with a few titles dating from the 1890s. Consisting largely of monographs, pamphlets, and serial issues, the collection contains a considerable number of publications issued by the Latvian Communist Party (Latvijas Komunistiskăs Partija or LKP), its youth wing (Latvijas Sociăldemokrătiskă Strădnieku Partija), and other associated organizations. There are also a few serial issues in the collection relating to the Latvian Social Democratic Workers Party (Latvijas Sociăldemokrătiskă Strădnieku Partija). In addition, there are monographs and pamphlets published when Latvia was part of the Soviet Union, as well as a number of publications emanating from the Latvian diaspora.
Administrative Information
Access
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Riga art historian and bibliophile.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ainar Ikstens collection is comprised of printed matter relating primarily to the history of Latvia in the 20th century, with a few titles dating from the 1890s. Consisting largely of monographs, pamphlets, and serial issues, the collection contains a considerable number of publications issued by the Latvian Communist Party (Latvijas Komunistiskăs Partija or LKP), its youth wing (Latvijas Komunistiskă Jaunatnes Savienība), and other associated organizations. There are also a few serial issues in the collection relating to the Latvian Social Democratic Workers Party (Latvijas Sociăldemokrătiskă Strădnieku Partija). In addition, there are monographs and pamphlets published when Latvia was part of the Soviet Union, as well as a number of publications emanating from the Latvian diaspora.
The collection has items from the tumultuous period surrounding Latvia's struggle for independence in the years 1917-1920, including a serial issue that published the decrees of the short-lived Soviet republic led by the Latvian communist Pēteris Stučka. The later Latvian Communist Party publications in the collection range from theoretical journals to bulletins distributed by regional sections of the party, as well as a circular issued by a factory committee in the Latvian capital, Rīga. Among the other rare and fugitive materials in the collection are a number of leaflets distributed by the LKP during the 1930s, when the party led a clandestine existence under the government of Kaārlis Ulmanis.
The underground leftist publications, pamphlets, leaflets, calendars, manuals, and ephemeral periodicals in this collection, which total more than one hundred items, cover the following main periods and topics, most of which are very poorly represented in academic libraries: publications of the 1917-19 turmoil in Latvia, underground leftist publications produced in Latvia or in the Soviet Union by the Communist International and directed against the Latvian government, brochures and periodicals from the first years of Soviet occupation, and selected Latvian émigré imprints.
The materials were obtained from Ainars Ikstens, a Latvian art historian and book collector. They are arranged according to physical form, and therein listed alphabetically by either author (monographs and pamphlets) or title (serial issues). When it is known, the Latvian name of the organization publishing a serial issue is also listed.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Latvia--Politics and government.; Latvia--History.; Socialism--Latvia.; Communism--Latvia.
Collection Contents
- Exhibit catalog, The History of Latvia in Cartoons: Celebrating 90 Years of the Republic of Latvia, 2007 (Folder 1: 1)
- Leaflets issued by the Latvian Communist Party and its youth organizations, 1936-1939 (Folder 1: 2)
- Monographs, 1921-1991 (Box 1)
  - Instruktsiia po emissionnno-kassovoi rabote, inkassatsii denezhnoi vyruchki i perevozke tsennostei v uchrezhdeniiakh Gosudarstvennogo Banka SSSR, 1971 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Latvijas PSR administratīvi teritoriālais iedalījums 1961. gads (Folder 1: 3)
  - Latvijas Skautu centrālās organizācijas. Iekārtas un darbības noteikumi, 1936 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Lielais Tēvijas karš un Padomju Latvijas inteliĤences uzdevumi: Latvijas PSR InteliĤences pirmais kongress 1945. g. 20.-22. III (Folder 1: 4)
  - Mūsu pienākums: Ko Latvija ražo, ko Latvija prasa, 1931 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Rīgas pilsētas II. Ĥimnāzija 1926-1933 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Sieviešu uzdevumi vācu okupācijas seku likvidēšanā Latvijā: Latvijas PSR InteliĤences pirmais kongress 1945. g. 20.-22.III (Folder 1: 6)
  - Beierbahs, K., Aizputes karš: Revolūcijas masustāsts 1905. g., 1933 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Dāle, P., Vēsturisks pārskats par Latvijas Augstskolas nodibināšanu un viņas darbību pirmā (1919./20.) mācības gadā, 1921 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Dubins, Herberts, Kreatīvas ceļš, 1991 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Eiduss, Zālamans, Valmieras varoņi, 1948 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Klētnieks, V., Latviešu skautisma trīsdesmit gadi 1917-1947 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Maldups, A., Valsts adresu kalendārs 1940. gadam (Folder 1: 9)
  - Menders, F., Ievads polītiskajā ekonomijā, 1930 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Simoni, L., Mirovoe evreistvo, evreiskaia natsiia ili Ostatok Izrailia, 1937 (Folder 2: 1)
- Pamphlets, 1893-1993 (Box 2)
  - XXIV. Konferentsia Kommunisticheckoi partii Latvii. Avgust 1927 g. Tezicy i resoliutsii (Folder 2: 2)
  - 1940. gada ārstniecības personāla un iestāžu saraksts (Folder 2: 2)
  - Apsūdzības raksts par vācu fašistisko iebrucēju ļaundarībām Latvijas, Lietuvas un Igaunijas PSR teritorijā, 1946 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Daugavas kalendārs 1917, 1916 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Istoriia Latvii-kratko i populiarno, 1992 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Kā imperiālisti organizē intervenziju pret SPRS un jaunu pasaules karu, 1930 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Ķeizariskās Krievijas Dārzkopības biedrības gada grāmata 1902 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Ķemeru sēravotu iestāde, 1940 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Ko Andrievs Niedra sludina?, 1904 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Kultūras Fonda III. Latvijas mākslas izstādes, 1936 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Latvia, 1962 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Latviešu skolotāju delegātu kongresa darbība un lēmumi. Tērbatā, no 8-13 junijam 1917. g. (Folder 2: 4)
  - Latvijas Republikas Aizsardzības ministrijas Darba pārskats (1991. gada novembris - 1993. gada jūnijs) (Folder 2: 5)
  - Latvijas Republikas Vides aizsardzības komitejas Darba pārskats (1991.-1992. gads), 1993 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Latvijas sasniegumi statistikas vērtējumā, 1939 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Latvijas skolotāju delegātu konference Rīgā no 2. līdz 5. janvārim 1919. g. (Folder 2: 6)
  - Latvijas zemnieku pļaujas svētki Koknesē, 1935 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Padomju Latvijas atdzimšanas ceļš, 1945 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Pagātnes ainas. J. Vientuļa sakopots vēsturisku dokumentu krājums, 1912 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Rasshirennyi plenum Ts.K. K.P.L. fevral'-mart 1930 g. Tezisy i resoliutsii (Folder 2: 7)
  - Rezoliutsii i postanovleniia. Rasshirennogo plenuma tsentral'nogo komiteta kommunisticheskoi partii latvii v fevrale 1932 g. (Folder 2: 7)
  - Strādnieku gada grāmata 1934 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Veselības aizsardzības izstāde, 1938 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Vēstures viltotāji, 1948 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Bakss, B., Parizes Komuna 1870- 1871. g., 1920 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Deglavs, Augusts, Latviešu attīstības solis no 1848. līdz 1875. g., 1893 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Jakobsone-Raine, G., No pirmās latviešu partizaņu brigādes pirmās vienības vēstures, 1953 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Jankavs, J., Darbs. Gada grāmata strādniekiem, 1907 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Kalniņš, Kārlis, Do you know that Latvia...?, 1940 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Kiršs, J., Kā laukstrādniekiem organizēties un cīnīties par sava stāvokļa uzlabošanu, 1930 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Kļaviņš J., Kā vācu okupanti un latviešu buržuāziskie nacionālisti izpostīja Latviju, 1946 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Klīve, Visvaldis, Sent in the World-Where and How?, 1970 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Klīve, Visvaldis, Svarīga izšķiršanās, 1964 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Krepp, E., Security and Non-Aggression: Baltic States and U.S.S.R. Treaties of Non-Aggression, 1973 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Kroders, Arturs, Par minoritatu autonomiju, 1924 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Lācis, V., Krievu un latviešu tautas vēsturiskā draudzība, 1945 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Lācis, V., Padomju Latvijas pieci gadi: Ziņojums Latvijas PSR Augstākās Padomes pirmā sasaukuma piektajā sesijā, 1945 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Lācis, V., Velikaia otechestvennaia voina i zadachi intelligentsia sovetsckoi Latvii, 1945 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Markov, M., Sovetskaia Latviia, 1940 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Mednis, Edvins, Gadu skrējiens: Rakstnieka atzīmes, 1947 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Menders, F., Sociālisms un zemniecība: Referāts Baltijas valstu sociālistisko studentu trešā kongresā Rīgā, 1930. gada 23. martā (Folder 3: 3)
  - Ozols, J., Spaidu režīms Latvijas cietumos, 1930 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Stepanovs, Politiskā ekonomika, 1918 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Stokmanis A. B., Skolēnu darbi vēsturē, 1927 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Stučka P., Piezīmes par agrāro (zemes) jautājumu, 1917 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Upīts, Andrejs, "Dzimtenes Vēstnesis" un viņa loma latviešu sadzīvē, 1911 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Virdheims, Anderss, Kas notiek ar Baltijas jūru, 1993 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Zeiferts, Teodors, Mūsu laikrakstu virzieni, 1896 (Folder 3: 4)
- Programs, 1942-1970 (Box 3)
  - Second Conference on Baltic studies, San Jose State College, San Jose, California, 1970 November 26-29 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Wintersportfest/Ziemas sporta svētki, Rīga, Latvia, 1942 February 7-8 (Folder 3: 5)
- Serial issues, 1910-1940 (Box 3)
  - 1. Maijs, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partijas Centrālā Komiteja, 1919 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Brīvība, Latvijas Sociālistiskā Strādnieku-Zemnieku Partija, no. 10, 1940 March (Folder 3: 6)
  - Darba Rīts, Latviešu Nacionālo Lietu Komisariāta Kultūras-Izglītības Nodaļa, no. 1., 1919 March (Folder 3: 6)
  - Darbs un Maize, Latvijas Partikas Komisariāts, nos. 1-2, 1919 February 15-22 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Latvijas Soziālistiskās Padomju Republikas Dekretu un Rīkojumu Krājums, nos. 1-7, 1919 February 14-April 30 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Hallo Latvija, 1941 (Folder 3: 8)
    - No. 10, 1941 July 19 (Folder 3: 8)
    - No. 13, 1941 August 16 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Jaunais Kocinieks (Rusk-Norskietis), Latvijas Komunistiskā Jaunatnes Savienība, I rajons, 1930 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Jaunatne, Latviešu Mācošās Jaunatnes Savienība, no. 1, 1918 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Jauni Ceļi, nos. 11-12, 1926 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kulturas Balss Apskats, 1919 November (Folder 3: 8)
  - Laima, Latvijas Komunistiskā Jaunatnes Savienība, Laimas fabrikas komiteja, no. 1, 1930 February (Folder 3: 9)
  - LKJS CK Biļetens, Latvijas Komunistiskā Jaunatnes Savienība, Centrālā Komiteja, no. 1, 1923 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Propagandists, Komunistiskās Internazionales Latvijas Sekzija, 1930-1931 (Folder 3: 9)
    - No. 6 (12), 1930 October (Folder 3: 9)
    - No. 2 (14), 1931 October (Folder 3: 9)
    - No. 3 (15), 1931 November (Folder 3: 9)
  - Revolucionārais Sociālists, Latvijas Sociālistiskās Strādnieku-Zemnieku Partijas un Sociālistiskās Jaunatnes Savienības Rīgas Organizācija, no. 2, 1934 September (Folder 3: 10)
  - Sarkanā Atbalss, Sarkanās Palīdzības Organizācija, nos. 1-2, 1926 March-June (Folder 3: 10)
  - Sarkanais Dzelzceļnieks, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partijas Rīgas komiteja un Pretfašisma organizācija, no. 6, 1935 January (Folder 3: 10)
  - Sarkanā Palīdzība, Sarkanās Palīdzības Organizācija, nos. 3-4/5, 1933 June-July/August (Folder 3: 11)
  - Sarkanais Kareivis, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partijas Kareivju organizācija, 1934-1935 (Folder 3: 11)
    - No. 11, 1934 August (Folder 3: 11)
    - No. 2, 1935 February (Folder 3: 11)
    - No. 5, 1935 June (Folder 3: 11)
  - Signāls, Rīgas Tautas Augstskolas audzēkņu padome, no. 4/5, 1935 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Šķiras Fronte, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partijas Rīgas komiteja, no. 7, 1936 October (Folder 3: 13)
  - Šoferis-Opozicionārs, šoferu arodopozīcijas, no. 2, 1936 January (Folder 3: 13)
  - SP Aktivists, Latvijas Sarkanā Palīdzība, no. 3, 1936 March (Folder 3: 13)
  - Spartaks, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partijas Rīgas komiteja, no. 2, 1919 December 12 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Strādnieks, Latvijas Komunistiskās Partija, no. 1, 1940 June (Folder 3: 14)
  - Vefists, 1935 November (Folder 3: 14)
  - Vienotais Arodnieks, no. 1, 1935 October (Folder 3: 14)
  - Zihna(Cīņa), Krievijas Sociāldemokrātiskā strādnieku partija, no. 100, 1910 July (Folder 3: 14)
- Incremental Materials (Box 4-5)